在前一讲中，我们研究了双关节机器人的工具提示速度。该
In the previous lecture, we looked at the tooltip velocity for a two-joint robot. The
末端效应器姿势由末端效应器坐标x和y描述，我们想出了表达式
end-effector pose is described by the end-effector coordinates x and y, and we came up with expressions
对于末端效应器姿势的变化率。这是x和x的变化率
for the rate of change of the end-effector pose. That is the rate of change of x and
根据机器人关节角度的变化率，y的变化率。我们做到了
the rate of change of y in terms of the rate of change of the robot joint angles. We did
类似于三关节机器人，其中描述了末端执行器姿势
a similar thing for the three-joint robot where the end-effector pose is described by
坐标x和y，以及方位角θ。并且，我们再次描述了x-dot，y-dot
a coordinate x and y, and an orientation angle, theta. And, we again described x-dot, y-dot
并且就机器人关节角度的变化率而言，θ点。
and theta-dot in terms of the rate of change of the robot’s joint angles.
现在，我们想为像这个Puma560机器人这样的六轴机器人做同样的事情。我们发现
Now, we want to do the same thing for a six-axis robot like this Puma 560 robot. We found out
这非常非常困难。必要的微积分和代数
that it is very, very difficult to do. The necessary differential calculus and algebra
将在我的笔记本中占用页面，页面和页面。这是一件非常困难的事情
is going to take up pages and pages and pages in my notebook. It is a very difficult thing
去做。因此，我们将研究另一种解决此问题的方法。
to do. So, we are going to look at an alternative way to crack this problem.
所以，我们现在想做的是了解关节速度之间的关系
So, what we want do now is to understand the relationship between the velocity of the joints
这个多关节机器人和末端执行器的速度，我们在其中描述
of this multi-jointed robot and the velocity of the end-effector, which we described in
它的x，y和z坐标的变化率和它的方向变化率。
terms of its rate of change of its x, y and z coordinates and rate of change of its orientation.
如果我们只看一个关节，这是我们将在这里使用的方法，
If we look at just a single joint, which is the approach we are going to use here,
我们可以看到，当我调整机器人的第一个关节时，我们可以看到末端效应器
we can see that as I adjust just the first joint of the robot, we can see that the end-effector
以弧线移动。因此，当我稍微调整一个关节时，我们看到x和
moves in an arc. And so, as I adjust joint one by a small amount, we see that the x and
末端效应器的y坐标发生变化。现在，如果我通过一个小调整第二个关节
y coordinates of the end-effector change. Now, if I adjust the second joint by a small
数量，我们可以看到末端效应器在垂直或z方向及其方向上发生变化
amount, we can see that the end-effector changes in the vertical or z direction and its orientation
也略有变化。对于第三个关节，我们可以遵循完全相同的论点
also changes slightly. We can follow exactly the same argument for the third joint of the
机器人，机器人的第四关节等。在你的第一个微积分课中，你会有
robot, fourth joint of the robot and so on. In your first calculus class, you would have
遇到这种关系。我们可以通过采用有限的方法来近似函数的导数
come across this relationship. We can approximate the derivative of a function by taking a finite
区别。在这种情况下，我们将x的值扰动少量deltax。而且，作为三角洲
difference. In this case, we perturb the value of x by a small amount, delta x. And, as delta
当x接近零时，x越来越小，我们有了真正的导数。
x gets smaller and smaller in the limit as it approaches zero, we have the true derivative.
我们要做的是计算正向运动函数的近似导数。
What we are going to do is to compute an approximate derivative of the forward kinematic function.
现在，我们已经介绍了前向运动学作为函数K和函数
Now, we have introduced previously the forward kinematics as a function K and function of
关节角度，它返回末端效应器的姿势。而且，你会注意到我有
the joint angles and it returns the end-effector pose. And, you will notice here that I have
使用偏导数表示法，因为运动函数是a的函数
used the partial derivative notation because the kinematic function is a function of a
向量Q.并且，我们将考虑关于一个特定的偏导数
vector Q. And, we are going to consider the partial derivative with respect to one particular
关节角度。所以，我们要做的是想出一个近似值
joint angle. So, what we are trying to do is to come up with an approximation for the
正向运动学随着单个关节的变化而变化的方式
way in which the forward kinematics changes as a function of variation of a single joint
角度。对于六轴机器人，我们将要治疗
angle. For the six-axis robot, we are going to treat
单独的关节，我们将从第一关节开始。所以，第一个
the joints individually and we are going to start with joint number one. So, the first
我们感兴趣的是，如果我调整第一关节，那有什么效果
thing that we are interested in is, if I adjust joint number one, what effect does that have
关于末端执行器的平移和角速度？在动画上
on the translational and angular velocity of the end-effector? In the animation on the
右手边，我们可以看到末端效应器的姿势随着我们进行小幅调整而改变
right hand side, we can see the end-effector pose changing as we make small adjustments
到第一个关节角度。那是Q1。让我们来看看它如何为Puma工作
to the first joint angle. That is Q1. Let us look at how this works for the Puma
560机器人。我要做的第一件事就是加载Puma560机器人的模型
560 robot. The first thing I am going to do is to load a model of the Puma 560 robot and
我们需要确定机器人将要进入的关节角度配置。您会注意到
we need to decide what joint angle configuration the robot is going to be in. You will notice
在工作区中有许多变量，如Qn，Qr，Qs和Qz以及这些变量
in the workspace that there are a number of variables like Qn, Qr, Qs and Qz and these
只是不同的机器人姿势。我们要使用的是Qn。那是
are just different robot poses. The one we are going to use is Qn. That is
Q名义空头。这是Puma机器人的姿势，有点在中间
short hand for Q nominal. This is a pose of the Puma robot that is somewhat in the middle
它的工作空间和非常灵巧的地方。它可以在很多不同的地方很好地移动
of its workspace and where it is very dexterous. It is able to move nicely in many different
方向。现在，我们要做的就是计算
directions. Now, we are going to do is to compute the
在该特定姿势的前向运动学，我们使用fkine方法来做到这一点。和，
forward kinematics at that particular pose and we use the fkine method to do that. And,
这里是表示为均匀变换矩阵的末端效应器姿势。现在，
here is the end-effector pose expressed as a homogeneous transformation matrix. Now,
我要做的是当我略微打扰关节角度时计算末端效应器的姿势。
what I am going to do is to compute the end-effector pose when I slightly disturb the joint angles.
所以，它将是关于姿势Qn。我要做的是添加一个向量
So, it is going to be about the pose Qn. What I am going to do is to add a vector to that
并且向量中的第一个元素是小位移。
and the first element in the vector is a small displacement.
现在，我将取代联合的一个。所以，我将为其余部分添加零
Now, I am going to displace joint one. So, I am going to add zero to the rest of the
机器人的关节。我们现在拥有的是一个非常小的变化的末端效应器姿势
robot’s joints. What we have now is the end-effector pose for a very small change
在第一关节的角度。我们扰乱了关节一个0.01弧度。和
in the angle of joint number one. We have disturbed joint one by 0.01 radians. And
在这里，我们可以看到末端效应器的姿势略有不同。
here, we can see that the end-effector pose is slightly different.
如果我们总结了我们刚刚在MATLAB中获得的标称关节的结果
If we summarised the results that we have just obtained in MATLAB for the nominal joint
这里由矢量Q给出的角度，这是机器人表达的末端效应器姿势
angle given here by the vector Q, this is the robot’s end-effector pose expressed
作为4×4同质转化基质。我们调整了Q非常小的数量。我们调整了
as a 4 x 4 homogenous transformation matrix. We adjusted Q by a very small amount. We adjusted
它是0.01弧度，大约是半度。当我们这样做时，我们获得了一个
it by 0.01 radians, which is around half a degree. When we did that, we obtained a
机器人的末端效应器姿势略有不同。我们可以看到数字
slightly different value for the robot’s end-effector pose. We can see that the numbers
在这两个矩阵中并不完全相同，这当然是我们所期望的
in those two matrices are not exactly the same and that is, of course, what we expect
因为我们改变了其中一个关节角度。现在的挑战是了解这是怎么回事
because we have changed one of the joint angles. The challenge now is to understand how this
变化与关节角度的变化有关。
change is related to the change in the joint angle.
我们现在要使用我们刚才介绍的表达方式
We are now going to use the expression we introduced a moment ago which relates the
函数的导数到函数的有限差分。如果我计算出有限的差异，
derivative of a function to a finite difference in a function. If I compute that finite difference,
我在这里得到了这个矩阵结果。当然，问题是这实际意味着什么？
I get this matrix result here. And the question is, of course, what does this actually mean?
如果我为同构变换矩阵编写符号表达式，我们记得
If I write the symbolic expression for a homogeneous transformation matrix, which we recall has
有一个3x3旋转组件和一个3x1平移组件，如果我采取
got a 3 x 3 rotational component and a 3 x 1 translational component, and if I take the
关于联合变量Q1的那个矩阵的导数，我可以写这个表达式
derivative of that matrix with respect to the joint variable Q1, I can write this expression
这里。现在，我们可以匹配此符号中的组件
here. Now, we can match the components in this symbolic
使用数值表达式中的组件表达式。所以，这是表达式-a
expression with the components in the numeric expression. So, this is the expression - a
T相对于Q1的偏导数，这里的这个位是偏导数
partial derivative of T with respect to Q1 and this bit here is the partial derivative
相对于Q1的旋转矩阵。让我们首先考虑翻译部分。
of the rotation matrix with respect to Q1. Let us consider first the translational part.
这是机器人末端执行器相对于Q1的偏导数。
Here is the partial derivative of the robot’s end-effector position with respect to Q1.
并且，如果我乘以Q1相对于时间的变化率，我最终会得到
And, if I multiply that by the rate of change of Q1 with respect to time, I end up with
翻译相对于时间的变化率，实际上是最终效应者的
the rate of change of translation with respect to time, which is in fact is the end-effector’s
平移速度。那是x-dot，y-dot和z-dot，我有时也会写
translational velocity. That is x-dot, y-dot and z-dot which I might also write sometimes
作为Vx，Vy或Vz。我可以重新排列这个表达式，我们有一个表达式的末端效应器
as Vx, Vy or Vz. I can rearrange this expression and we have an expression for the end-effector
恒定矢量的速度乘以关节1的速度。
velocity in terms of a constant vector multiplied by the velocity of joint one.
您注意到这里有一个近似符号。重要的是要记住
You notice that there is an approximation sign in here. It is important to remember
我们在这里计算了一个有限差分。它是真实导数的近似值。
that we have computed a finite difference here. It is an approximation to the true derivative.
我们使用了0.01弧度的关节角度变化。而且，当我们在关节角度上做出改变时
We used a change in joint angle of 0.01 radians. And, as we make that change in joint angle
越来越小，我们将得到更接近真实导数的近似值。但，
smaller and smaller, we will get a better approximation to the true derivative. But,
如果我们把它做得太小，我们会因为算术的方式而遇到数值误差
if we make it too small, we will encounter numerical errors because of the way arithmetic
是在数字计算机内完成的，我们需要找到某种平衡。所以，请继续
is done inside a digital computer and we need to find some sort of balance. So, keep in
请记住，我们在这里所做的是对真实关系的近似。
mind that what we have done here is an approximation to the true relationship.
我们有相关的末端效应器翻译速度和Q1的变化率
We have related end-effector translational velocity to rate of change of Q1 and we can
为联合二和联合三一直到第六联合做这个。找到表达式
do this for joint two and for joint three all the way up to joint six. Find the expressions
将关节​​速度与末端效应器平移速度联系起来。
that relate joint velocity to end-effector translational velocity.
现在让我们考虑旋转部分。而且，这并不是那么简单。这里，
Let us now consider the rotational part. And, this is not quite as straightforward. Here,
我已经写出了旋转矩阵相对于关节角度的偏导数
I have written the partial derivative of a rotation matrix with respect to joint angle
一。并且，如果我乘以关节1的变化率与时间相乘，
one. And, if I multiply that by the rate of change of joint one with respect to time,
我最终得到了旋转矩阵相对于时间的变化率。有一个众所周知的
I end up with the rate of change of the rotation matrix with respect to time. There is a well-known
旋转矩阵的变化率，角速度之间的关系
relationship between the rate of change of the rotation matrix, the angular velocity
欧米茄和旋转矩阵本身。而且，我们可以在这里替换它。矩阵
omega and the rotation matrix itself. And, we can substitute that in here. The matrix
S是我们所说的偏斜对称矩阵，它是角速度的函数
S is what we called a skew symmetric matrix and it is a function of the angular velocity
矢量欧米茄。
vector omega.